Finding Aid for Martha Cook Building (University of Michigan) records, 1914-1981, 2013-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Martha Cook Building (University of Michigan) records Summer 1967
University of Michigan. Martha Cook building.
1 oversize box
7.25 linear feet
Bimu F17 2
The records of the Martha Cook Building at the University of Michigan (women's dormitory) contains adminsitrative files and historical information about the construction of the building.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group has been donated by the Board of Governors of the Martha Cook Building in several accessions (Donor # 5887 ).in several accessions.
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted to protect individual privacy. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws.
The following are terms of restriction for specific genres of records found in this record group:
student records are restricted for fifty years from date of creation.
The record group University of Michigan Martha Cook Building contains contains 2 folders of restricted student related files coverd by FERPA; these files have been removed to the vault.
The Martha Cook Building opened in the fall of 1915 as the second all-women's dormitory on the University of Michigan campus. It was a gift of Mr. William Wilson Cook, a lawyer-philanthropist from New York City who was born and raised in Hillsdale, Michigan. He graduated from the University of Michigan with A.B. and L.L.B. degrees before going on to work in Toledo and then New York City. He became a prominent lawyer and later wrote several books. The last years of Mr. Cook's life were spent studying, reading, writing, and supervising his building projects at the university, including the Martha Cook Building and the Law Quadrangle.
William Cook named the dormitory after his mother, Martha Wolford Cook. As her husband was often away, Martha Cook had the primary responsibility of raising their nine children, William being the third oldest. Mr. Cook was obviously inspired by his mother. The home he built for female students in her memory was intended to provide a unique atmosphere in which "the charm and grace and principles of cultured American womanhood" (Macklin and Chamberlain The Martha Cook Building, p. 4) would be developed. He felt that intellect was important, but he valued character and womanly grace above it.
The building itself was said to be the finest of its type in the nation at the time it was built. Various styles are represented throughout the building, ranging from the Gothic exterior to interiors from Early Renaissance and Tudor Gothic to furnishings from Jacobean and later periods. In one room hangs a life-size portrait of Martha Wolford Cook, which was intended "to portray an epoch in which the mother was queen in her home, respected for the simplicity of her manners and the greatness of her virtues" (ibid., 6). Furniture and accessories include Chinese pottery, sixteenth century Italian sofas, Jacobean chairs, oak tables, a replica of the Venus de Milo carved in Italy from Carrara marble, and a specially-designed Steinway piano inlaid with Circassian walnut. A statue of Portia stands over the front door.
Originally, residency in MCB was offered to senior women only. Eventually, other upperclassmen, graduate students, and freshmen were allowed to live there as well. Because there was often a lengthy waiting list, applicants were assigned points, in part based on their year in school and their grades, and were required to provide a biographical sketch of themselves. The point totals and sketches were used to determine who filled any vacancies that occurred. Over the years a number of Martha Cook Building traditions have developed, including a special dinner for new women in the fall, Friday afternoon tea, a "Messiah Dinner" near Christmas, the Christmas Breakfast, and a Senior Dinner.
Much of the historical sketch above was taken from The Martha Cook Building, by Wystan Stevens, 1976, and The Martha Cook Building, by Elaine Macklin and Tenney Chamberlain, 1970. Copies of both publications may be found in Box 8, under Histories.
The records of the first accession span the years 1913 to 1972 and are arranged in the order in which they were received. They cover a broad spectrum of subjects and include substantive records in the Board of Governors, William W. Cook, and the building itself. The first accession contains the following series: Board of Governors Files, Correspondence, Papers, Administrative Records, Reports, Activity Files, and Visual Materials.
Records received in the 1993 accession span the years 1915 to 1990 but are primarily from 1973 to 1979 when Olive Chernow was director of the building.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Martha Cook building.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; Dormitories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Condon House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Construction industry--1915.; Costumes.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Martha Cook building.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; Dormitories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Cook, William W. (William Wilson), 1858-1930.
Genre Terms:
College publications.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Papers, 1913-1972
  The PAPERS series (1 linear foot 1913-1972), arranged by date received, contains files on the construction of the building, including correspondence with the architects, and specifications and blueprints. It also contains papers related to receptions, petitions for house offices, room lists, and miscellaneous papers and correspondence.
  - 1913-1965
    - 1916-1947 (Box 1)
      (concerning gift of a residential hall to the University of Michigan by William W. Cook, and a list of Board of Governors at Martha Cook Building).
    - Meeting 1937 of Resolutions Committee, Student Board and Board of Governors (Box 1)
    - Construction of Martha Cook Building
      - Correspondence with Architects 1913-1918, 4 folders (Box 1)
      - Specifications 1915 (Box 1)
      - Blueprints (Box 1)
  - 1916-1972
    - Correspondence regarding Portia-statue 1917-1918 (Box 4)
    - List of books sent to Martha Cook Building 1916 (Box 4)
    - Receptions
      - Ossip Gabrilowitsch 1927 (Box 4)
      - Cornelia Otis Skinner 1930 (Box 4)
      - Mrs. Codd 1934 (Box 4)
      - Miss Gleason 1936 (Box 4)
    - Petitions for Office
      - President 1956-1959 (Box 4)
      - Vice President 1956-1959 (Box 4)
      - Judiciary 1961-1964, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Secretary 1961-1967 (Box 4)
      - Treasurer 1958-1968, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - House Service 1958-1968 (Box 4)
    - Alumnae replies to Victory Reunion Invitation 1946 (Box 4)
    - Etiquette Suggestions (Box 4)
    - Night Receptionist's Duties (Box 4)
    - Summer Letters 1955-1970 (Box 4)
    - Social Calendar 1966-1971 (Box 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Room Lists 1927-1972 (Box 4)
    - Fiftieth Anniversary of the Martha Cook Building 1965, 1 volume (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook: "In Memoriam, William Wilson Cook" (Box 5)
- Board of Governors Files 1930-1973, 2013-2014
  The BOARD OF GOVERNORS series (.25 linear feet, 1930-1973), arranged chronologically, consists of meeting minutes.
  - Minutes
    - 1933-1937 (Box 1)
    - 1937-1939 (Box 1)
    - 1949-1973, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - June 14, 2013-June 13, 2014 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1941-1968
  The CORRESPONDENCE series (.5 linear feet, 1914-1968), arranged thematically, contains the Board of Governors correspondence, correspondence of the Business Office, miscellaneous correspondence, and the William W. Cook files containing both correspondence and news clippings from 1914 to 1930. Although contained in its own series, various types of correspondence are scattered throughout the accession.
  - Correspondence 1951-1968 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with the University of Michigan
    - 1930-1936 (Box 1)
    - 1935-1940 (Box 1)
    - 1941-1945 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence
    - 1936-1939 (Box 1)
    - 1945-1949 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1932-1955 (Box 1)
  - William W. Cook Files
    - Correspondence
      - 1914-1928 (Box 1)
      - 1928-1929 (Box 1)
      - 1929-1930 (Box 1)
    - News clippings (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1915-1920 of Mr. & Mrs. Chauncey F. Cook (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with members of the Board of Governors
    - Mrs. Frederic Beckwith Stevens 1922-1934 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Harry C. Bulkley 1929-1933 (Box 1)
    - Miss Emilie G. Sargent 1929-1934 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Stuart Baits 1932-1934 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. James D. Bruce 1933-1934 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Florentine Cook Heath 1933-1938 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Edward D. Maire 1937-1939 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Chauncey F. Cook, Jr. 1939-1943 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1915-1927 of the Business Office (Box 1)
- Administrative Records
  The ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS (1 linear foot, 1915-1966) consists of financial statements, social directors' notebooks, house director's notebooks, and the president and vice presidents' reports.
  - Financial Statements
    - 1915-1921 (Box 2)
    - 1922-1927 (Box 2)
    - 1928-1929 (Box 2)
  - Social Directors Notebooks (Reports, etc.)
    - 1928-1956, 5 volumes (Box 2)
  - President's Reports 1929-1958, 1965-1966, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Vice-President's Reports 1939-1957, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - House Director's Notebooks 1933-1949, 2 volumes (Box 2)
- Reports 1931-1965
  The REPORTS series (.5 linear feet, 1931-1965), arranged thematically, consist of the secretary's reports, treasurer's reports, and activity reports. These include summaries of their activities during the year, as well as their opinions as to the success of various events.
  - Secretary's Reports 1938-1965 (Box 3)
  - Treasurer's Reports 1931-1962 (Box 3)
  - Activity Reports
    - Activities Chairman 1958-1962 (Box 3)
    - Alumnae Secretary 1957-1962 (Box 3)
    - Assembly Dormitory Council 1953-1964 (Box 3)
    - Athletics Chairman 1952-1963 (Box 3)
    - Choir Director 1951-1960 (Box 3)
    - Chorister 1935-1962 (Box 3)
    - Coke Machine Chairman 1955-1962 (Box 3)
    - Cultural Events Chairman 1951-1963 (Box 3)
    - House Service Chairman 1958-1963 (Box 3)
    - Internal Publicity Chairman 1948-1965 (Box 3)
    - International Chairman 1958-1961 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Musical Events Chairman 1951-1963 (Box 3)
    - Scholarship Chairman 1951-1961 (Box 3)
    - Senior Representative 1946-1956 (Box 3)
    - T.V. and Phonograph 1956-1962 (Box 3)
- Activity Files 1934-1970
  The ACTIVITY FILES series (.75 linear feet, 1934-70), arranged alphabetically, documents dormitory events from 1934 to 1970. Some documented events were held annually, others only once.
  - Alumnae, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Alumnae Newsletter 1960-1963 (Box 3)
  - Alumnae Tea 1957-1962 (Box 3)
  - Art Exhibits 1952-1956 (Box 3)
  - Assembly Ball Cocktail Party 1950-1957 (Box 3)
  - Assembly Ball Dinner 1955-1957 (Box 3)
  - Birthday Dinners 1950-1963 (Box 3)
  - Blue Book Revision 1958-1963 (Box 3)
  - Canoe Trip 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - Caroling parties 1957-1959 (Box 3)
  - Christmas Breakfast 1939-1968 (Box 3)
  - Christmas Buffet Supper 1959-1961 (Box 3)
  - Christmas Card Lists 1956-1960 (Box 3)
  - Coke Party 1967 (Box 3)
  - Cook Memorial Service 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - Dessert for New Women 1968 (Box 3)
  - Easter Egg Hunt 1951 (Box 3)
  - Election Campaign 1949-1958 (Box 3)
  - Election Listening Party 1956 (Box 3)
  - Exchange Dinners 1947-1965 (Box 3)
  - Faculty Dinner Parties 1941-1959 (Box 3)
  - Faculty Dinners (Box 3)
  - Football Open Houses 1955-1964 (Box 3)
  - Formal Dinner for New Women 1939-1970 (Box 3)
  - Fortnite Skit Reports 1951-1958 (Box 3)
  - Gold Room Party 1961 (Box 3)
  - Homecoming Display 1948-1962 (Box 3)
  - Informal Dances, etc. 1937-1950 (Box 3)
  - International Student Party 1965 (Box 3)
  - Invitations Committee 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - Lantern Night (Box 3)
  - Lawyer's Tea 1959-1967 (Box 3)
  - Library and Scrapbook Reports 1940-1960 (Box 3)
  - Magazines 1951-1961 (Box 3)
  - Marriages and Births (Box 3)
  - May Basket (Box 3)
  - May Party Reports 1940-1947 (Box 3)
  - Michigras 1948-1958 (Box 3)
  - Ministers' Dinner 1954-1958 (Box 3)
  - Mother's Weekend 1965 (Box 3)
  - Open House 1941-1956, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Orientation 1955 (Box 4)
  - Scholarship Tea 1962-1963 (Box 4)
  - Senior Dinner 1934-1961, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Senior Night (Box 4)
  - Sorority Exchange Dinner 1955-1956 (Box 4)
  - Spring formal 1952-1964, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Square Dance-Tennis Court 1955-1966 (Box 4)
  - Staff Dinner 1960-1961 (Box 4)
  - Student addresses 1957-1961 (Box 4)
  - Tea for Board of Governors (Box 4)
  - Tea for Coop Women (Box 4)
  - Tea for New Women 1949-1965, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Teas for Directors and Presidents 1951-1960 (Box 4)
  - Twenty-fifth Anniversary 1940 (Box 4)
  - Valentine Buffet 1960 (Box 4)
  - Valentine Dinner 1948-1953 (Box 4)
  - Vesper Services 1934 (Box 4)
- Visual Materials
  The VISUAL MATERIALS series (2 linear feet, undated), arranged alphabetically, includes negatives, photographs (mostly black and white), and prints of furnishings, architecture, people and activities. The negatives are from 1965, but the majority of photographs are undated. In addition, there is VHS tape of the 75th anniversary celebration in 1990, and a scrapbook pertaining to William Wilson Cook's financial and building donations to the university.
  - Negatives October 1965, 10/1965 by U-M News Service; activities; (in 20 strips, of furnishings and architecture; people); 109 negatives (Box 5)
  - Photographs
    - Building
      - Exterior
        - General, 14 images, mostly black and white 8x10 (Box 5)
        - Construction views, see na 9281-9282; 9 images; mostly black and white 8x10 (Box 5)
      - Interior
        - Corridor, Right, 4 images, mostly black and white 7x9 (Box 5)
        - Dining Room, 1 image black and white 8x10 (Box 5)
        - Dormitory area, 1 image black and white 5x7 (Box 5)
        - Large Parlor (Blue/Gold Room), 8 images, mostly black and white 8x10 (Box 5)
        - Small Parlor (Red Room), 1 images black and white 8x10 (Box 5)
    - Martha Cook (Box 5)
    - Costumes, see na 9280; 11 black and white 4x6 (Box 5)
    - Garden, see na 9283; 19 images; mostly & black and white 8x10; 5x7 (Box 5)
      (includes gardens of Martha Cook Building and Condon House)
    - Groups, 1; mostly color 8x10; 6 black and white (Box 5)
    - Individuals, 23 proofs, approx 2x2-1/2; 12 images of varying size black and white (Box 5)
    - May Day Party May 26, 1928, see na 9278-9279; 41 images, mostly & ;collage black and white 4x5; 2x4 (Box 5)
    - Sculptures, 5 images of Portia, varying size black and white (Box 5)
  - Prints, 7 images 5x7 (Box 5)
  - Videotape (VHS)-75th anniversary celebration 1990 (Box 5)
  - Photographs/Prints-Outsize
    - Building
      - Interior (Box 6)
      - Exterior (Box 6)
    - Groups (Box 6)
    - Martha Cook (Box 6)
    - Sculptures (Box 6)
- Chronological Files
  The CHRONOLOGICAL FILES series (.25 linear feet, 1969-1980), arranged chronologically, is comprised of various correspondence, social calendars, activity reports, and other miscellanea from 1969 to 1980. Although not complete in their coverage of any given year's activities, they provide an interesting look at the various events that took place in the Martha Cook Building.
  - Chronological Files 1969-1980, 7 folders (Box 7)
- Minutes of House Board 1963-2006
  The MINUTES OF THE HOUSE BOARD series (.25 linear feet, 1963-1981), arranged chronologically, documents the meetings held by the House Board, which is composed of residents. The minutes provide an inside look at life in the dormitory, including the daily concerns of residents, rules and regulations, and preparations for social activities.
  - Minutes of the House Board 1963-1981, 12 folders (Box 7)
  - Minutes of the House Board 1999-2006, 14 folders (Box 7)
- Topical Files
  The TOPICAL FILES series (.5 linear feet, 1915-1990), arranged alphabetically consists of documentation on the duties of the director and other staff, including a procedures manual, a daily activity log, correspondence, a social activities log, and purchasing and maintenance records. Within the miscellaneous folder there is a particularly interesting account of the architecture and furnishings of the Martha Cook Building.
  - 1915-1993
    - Anne E. Shipman Stevens Scholarship Applications 1976-1980
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2055 ]
    - Awards and Scholarships 1933 (Box 7)
    - Barbara Hansen Student Material 1953-1955 (Box 7)
    - Blue Books (Regulations, Constitution, & Bylaws), undated 1972-1980 (Box 7)
    - Board of Governors 1979 (Box 7)
    - Cook Family and Cook House, undated 1974-1977 (Box 7)
    - Detroit Alumnae of the Martha Cook Building 1965-1981 (Box 7)
    - Director (Box 7)
    - General 1965-1979 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence 1974-1979 (Box 7)
    - Daily Activity Log 1974-1975 (Box 7)
    - Procedures Manual 1979
    - Fimian Bequeathment 1982-1984 (Box 8)
    - Harriet L. Blum Memorial Scholarship Fund 1958-1969 (Box 8)
    - Hillsdale College 1974 (Box 8)
    - Isabel K. Quail Scholarship Fund 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - Lease undated (Box 8)
    - Maintenance Log 1964-1974 (Box 8)
    - Messiah Dinner 1965-1975 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, undated 1940-1976 (Box 8)
    - Nancy Howe Bielby Sudin, Student Contracts for Martha Cook 1954 (Box 8)
    - News Articles 1915-1989 (Box 8)
    - Purchasing Log 1963-1975 (Box 8)
    - Recreation Survey undated (Box 8)
    - Residence Applications 1979
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2056 ]
    - 75th Jubilee Report 1990 (Box 8)
    - Social Activities Log 1970-1977 (Box 8)
    - Songs undated (Box 8)
    - University Residence Hall Council 1980 (Box 8)